Guide to the Robert L. McCaul, Jr. Papers 1900-1994
University of Chicago Library
- Series V: Writings and Speeches
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 10 – Typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 10 – Photocopy, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 11 – Typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 11 – Photocopy, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 12 – Typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 12 – Photocopy, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Appendix I: Statistical Tables – Typescripts, Photocopies, Notes [1 of 2], undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Appendix I: Statistical Tables – Typescripts, Photocopies, Notes [2 of 2], undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Appendix Revisions – Typescripts and Photocopies, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Unidentified Chapter – Partial Typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Front Matter, Introduction, Brochure (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 1, Original – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 1 – Typescript Photocopy with Revisions (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 2 – Typescript and Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 2 – Photocopy with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 3 – Typescript and Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 3 – Photocopy with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 4 – Typescript and Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 4 – Photocopy with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 5 – Typescript and Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 6 – Typescript and Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Blacks, the Civil War and Public Schools – Chapter 6 – Photocopy with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - "Charles Hubbard Judd" (for Dictionary of American Biography) – Typescripts, Correspondence, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - "Charles Hubbard Judd, 1873-1946" – Journal, Typescripts, Correspondence, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - "Dewey at Chicago" (from "Dewey to Mid-Career, 1859-1904") – Typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - "Dewey and the University of Chicago" – Journals, Reprints, Photocopy, Notes, 1961, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Dewey Book – Chapter I – Manuscript [1 of 2], undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Dewey Book – Chapter I – Manuscript [2 of 2], undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Dewey Book – 1866-1876 – Notes and Source Material, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Dewey Book – Chapter "1866-1876" – Manuscript, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Dewey Book – "School Years 1876-1877, 1881" Chapter – Manuscript, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Dewey Book – Notes and Clipping, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - "Dewey in College, 1875-79" – Journal, Reprints, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - "Dewey Leaves Chicago"/"Dewey and the University of Chicago" – Typescripts, Proof, Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - "Dewey's Chicago" – Reprints, 1959 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - "Dewey's Decade at the University of Chicago: The Quest for Unity and Identity" – Correspondence, Source Materials, circa 1982 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - "Dewey's Decade at the University of Chicago: The Quest for Unity and Identity" – Typescripts and Photocopies, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - "Dewey's School Days, 1867-1875" – Reprints, 1962 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - "Dewey to Mid-Career, 1859-1904" – Typescript Draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - A Documentary History of Education in Colonial Georgia – McCaul Thesis Proposal, Abstract, and Corrections, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - A Documentary History of Education in Colonial Georgia – McCaul Dissertation – Typescript, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - "Education and the Social Order: The Chicago Experience" – Conference Talk – Typescripts and Correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - "Education in Georgia during the Period of Royal Control, 1752-1776" – Part I – Journals, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - "Education in Georgia during the Period of Royal Control, 1752-1776" – Part II – Journals, Typescripts, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Education in the Colonial South (excerpt from The American Educational Tradition – Typescript, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - "Educational Biography: Dewey and Howe" – Journal and Photocopies, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - "Educational News and Editorial Comment" – Journal, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - "Elizabeth Harrison" and "Alice Harvey Whiting Putnam" – Typescripts and Correspondence, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - First Chicago High School – Preface – Typescript and Photocopy, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - First Chicago High School – Preface and Chapter I – Manuscript, Notes, and Source Material [1 of 3], undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - First Chicago High School – Preface and Chapter I – Manuscript, Notes, and Source Material [2 of 3], undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - First Chicago High School – Preface and Chapter I – Manuscript, Notes, and Source Material [3 of 3], undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - First Chicago High School – Preface, Chapters 1 and 2 – Photocopy, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - First Chicago High School –Chapter I – Typescript and Photocopy, undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - First Chicago High School –Chapter II – Typescript (Rough) Draft with Notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - First Chicago High School –Chapter II – Typescript, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - First Chicago High School –Chapter II – Partial Photocopy, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - "Historical and Philosophical Foundations of Education" – Journal and Reprints, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - "A History of an Urban System of School Governance" (Havinghurst Festschrift) – Typescripts, Correspondence, Clippings [1 of 2], 1971-1992 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - "A History of an Urban System of School Governance" (Havinghurst Festschrift) – Typescripts [2 of 2], 1971-1992 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Preface – Manuscript, Typescript and Photocopy, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Preface and Chapter I – Manuscript and Typescript Draft, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter I –Typescript and Photocopy, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter II –Typescript Draft, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter II –Typescript and Photocopy, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter III –Typescript Draft, Corrections, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter IV –Typescript Draft, undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter IV –Typescript and Photocopy, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter IV –Carbon Copy, Notes, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter V –Typescript and Photocopy, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter V –Carbon Copy, Notes, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter V –Typescript, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter VI –Typescript with Notes, Source Material [1 of 2], undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter VI –Typescript with Notes [2 of 2], undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter VI –Typescript, Notes, Tables [1 of 2], undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter VI –Typescript, Notes [2 of 2], undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Chapter VI –Carbon Copy, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - A History of the Public Schools of Chicago, 1834-1900 – Partial Photocopy, undated (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - "Interaction between Society and Education in Chicago" (Havinghurst, McCaul, and Murray) – US Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Report, Typescript, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Interview re Dewey – Lab Notes Vol. 11, No. 2, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - "Introducing Harold B. Dunkel" – Typescript, Notes, Correspondence, Journal, 1977-1990 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Judd Dinner Speech – Typescripts, Correspondence, Article, 1973-1992 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - "Manual Training" – Manuscript [1 of 2], undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - "Manual Training" – Manuscript [2 of 2], undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - "On the Origins and Nature of Educational Leadership" (NSSE Yearbook) Woodring and McCaul – Typescripts, Memoranda, Clippings, 1967-1981 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Power and Community in Struggles for Equal Rights: The Blacks' Effort to Win Public Schooling and Other Rights in 19th Century Illinois – Photocopied Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois) [1 of 3], undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Power and Community in Struggles for Equal Rights: The Blacks' Effort to Win Public Schooling and Other Rights in 19th Century Illinois – Photocopied Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois) [2 of 3], undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Power and Community in Struggles for Equal Rights: The Blacks' Effort to Win Public Schooling and Other Rights in 19th Century Illinois – Photocopied Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois) [3 of 3], undate (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - "A Preliminary Listing of Dewey Letters, 1894-1904" – Correspondence, Typescript, Journals, Reprints, 1959 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - "Presidential Elections and the Vote, 1892 to 1956" – Reprints, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Remarks at Francis S. Chase Dinner – Typescripts, Memos, 1964 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - "Rome Killed Francis Hanford" – Manuscript, Typescripts, Clipping, 1973-1988 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - "Social Tolerance, Pedagogical Tolerance" – University of Chicago High School Graduation Day Address – Typescript, Programs, Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Research Correspondence, 1972-1981 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Publisher and Reader Correspondence, 1978-1983 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – Introduction, Multiple Revisions – Typescripts, Photocopies (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1977-1978 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Introduction and Chapter 1– Typescript with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 2 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Effort to Win Public-School Rights for Illinois Blacks, 1800-1875 – Chapter 2, Revision B, Summer – Typescript and Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 3 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 4 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 5 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 6 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 7 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 8 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 9 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 10 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 11 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Blacks, the Public Schools, and the Law, Illinois, 1800-1875 – March 1978 Revision – Chapter 12 – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Effort to Win Public-School Rights for Illinois Blacks, 1800-1875 – Appendix, Revision B, Summer – Typescripts (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1978 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Effort to Win Public-School Rights for Illinois Blacks, 1800-1875 – Chapter 2, Revision – Typescript Fragments (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1979 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 1 Revision – Typescript and Manuscript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1980 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 2 Revision – Typescript, Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1980 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 2 Revision – Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1980 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Preface – Typescripts with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981-1982 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 1 Revision – Carbon Copy and Manuscript Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 2 Revision – Typescript Fragments with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 3, 1980-1981 Revision, "1st Typed Copy" – Typescript with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 3, "2nd Typed Copy, Final" – Typescript, Manuscript Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 4, "1980-1981 Revision, Original" – Typescript, Manuscript Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 4 Revision, "Final" – Typescript, Manuscript Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 4 Revision, "Final" – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 5, "1981 Revision, Copy 1" – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 6, Revision – Typescripts, Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 6, Chapter 5 Footnotes – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 7, Revision – Typescript with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 7, Revision – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 9, Revision – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1981 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 6,"Original Manuscript Revised" – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1982 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 7, "1981-1982 Revision, Final" – Typescript with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1982 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 7, Revision – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1982 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Preface – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 1 Revision – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 2 Revision – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 3, "Final 1983 Revision" – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 4 Revision – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 5 Revision – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 6, Revision – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 8, "1982-1983 Revision" – Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 9, "1982-1983 Revision" – Typescript with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1983 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 8, Revision – Typescript with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), 1984 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Struggle for Schooling: Blacks, Whites, and the Uses of Power in 19th Century Illinois – Typescript [1 of 3], 1985 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Struggle for Schooling: Blacks, Whites, and the Uses of Power in 19th Century Illinois – Typescript [2 of 3], 1985 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Struggle for Schooling: Blacks, Whites, and the Uses of Power in 19th Century Illinois – Typescript [3 of 3], 1985 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Publisher Correspondence, Reader Reports, Author Questionnaire, 1985-1986 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Clippings and Address Lists, 1985-1987 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Endnotes and Bibliography – Carbon Copies, 1986 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Front Matter and Introduction – Typescript with Revisions, undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - The Struggle for Schooling – Introduction – Notes and Manuscripts under Various Titles [1 of 2], undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - The Struggle for Schooling – Introduction – Notes and Manuscripts under Various Titles [2 of 2], undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 1 "Final Original Copy" – Typescript Fragments (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Effort to Win Public-School Rights for Illinois Blacks, 1800-1875 – Chapter 1, Revision B – Typescript Fragments, Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois) [1 of 2], undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Effort to Win Public-School Rights for Illinois Blacks, 1800-1875 – Chapter 1, Revision B – Notes and Sources (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois) [2 of 2], undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Chapter 5 "Rough Draft, Final" – Typescript with Notes (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Struggle for Schooling – Appendix Tables – Typescripts (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Struggle for Schooling: The Effort to Win Public-School Rights for Illinois Blacks, 1800-1875 – Front Matter and Preface – Photocopies of Typescript (Later The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois), undated (Box 27, Folder 8)